yeah
in this video we are going to be adding is moving to our camera as as you can
see up here
maybe it's a little hard but our level is larger than the actual cameras view
port here
the line goes down here and here we would like to be able to move the camera
around here so that we can see the whole level so that we're not bound to make
levels that has the size of the camera width and height and so we can make a
slightly less one and we can just move around with the camera to place towers
on the map
so to do this we will have to create a new script and the script should be
called camera movement so go to script folder right-click grade and see our
script and called camera movement
when you create that's what we need to write some code and basically this code
on goes right here is going to be very simple and so maybe you already know how
to do all this but it will be more complicated later when we need to
restrict the bounds of the camera so that it can't go off the map but right
now we're just going to add the functionality so that it can actually
move in within the and outside the bounds from them as well
so first of all we need a speed so make a private float called camera speed and
set it equal to 0 from the get-go because then considered in our inspector
and and it just it from there
when you have set to 0 we need to be able to see the inspector so we're going
to serialize the field as we usually do when we need to access something from
the inspector immunity
so the next thing we are going to do is to create a functional private void get
input and this function here will take the place input and actually move the
camera around
so first of all we need to make some if statements yet and this is the reason
that I'm doing this is because it makes it easier for us to clamp their them
what's called the position later but for now make an if statement
so if input that get key down key code to tell you if we press the w button
well then we say transformed to translate
it's a free that up x
camera speed
x time . Delta time I so
ok so now we can actually move upwards and the point is that this translate
transform the translator will move the camera around on the screen based on
whatever we tell you to do in here inside the parameters
so we tell it to move upwards when first w button and we multiplied with the
camera speed and x time to time so time to time is the amount of time that has
passed since last time update was called and by multiplying by that
there we will talk account for the time so that the camera will move the same
speed on all your devices
so if we run mobile phone that hasn't it that isn't as powerful as computer in
the home computer as I'm sitting out here at the camera might want faster on
the computer
if we don't take the time into account so that's why we are multiplying but
time that Delta time anyway this was w we actually just copy and paste this
three times
underneath and then w.e this empty
so now we have wasd and on a way of course me to go to the left so we write
left here on s way to go down and on
do you need to go to the right so now you actually have the code for moving
the camera from side to side but right now we're not executing get input
anywhere but we need this code to be executed search executed we need to go
to update and right get input
like so so now we have our get input functionality and he needs that actually
we can write private here just to just put measure
so now we have the input function so if we save this and go to unity
well then this script here actually take the transformed to translate from it and
move the transform on the object it's sitting on and we wanted to move the
camera so we take the camera script and move it onto the camera so that it has
that their script on it and if we just play the game now you will not be able
to move anywhere and that's because the camera has zero speed
so to give the camera some speed we can simply just a five for example and then
your camera is able to move but you can see here you can hold down the key
you have to let go and click the key and to move around and that's because I
wrote some from quote i used input to get key down instead of get key
so the code is only a secure right when we click the button
use the input that get you down which means this code here for moving the
camera gets executed right when employed press the key down and then it stops
so we need to write get key instead
like so so we can replace all the gate key down with get key
there we go and then save and then we jump back to unity and remember to
select the main camera and put a speed if you didn't do it before because you
can see if i put five speed here and I stopped playing the game that it reverts
back to zero so i can put five before I play the game then it stays 5 and now i
can see and hold down the button here to pan around on the on the map here but
our movement is not restricted at all
we can simply move all the edges of the of the man everything so we need to do
something so that we restrict the cameras movement
so let's try to do that so to make sure that our camera doesn't move over the
edges of our map we will have to make sure that we can take on screen
coordinates and translate them into world coordinates so that we know we
don't pass the edge of the map because if you look here you can see I know it's
very hard to see but we have our camera
the white line here and this white line is never supposed to pass the bottom
right corner here because if you do so then does so then we can actually see
that blue edge and on around on man we're not it
we're not interested in that we would like the camera only to go to about here
something so that it never goes over the edge of the actual level and this will
be way more precise of course so that it doesn't go over at all on the map
so to do so we will have to understand how we could translate onto in
coordinates to world coordinates and you so we will have to use something called
you to work in newport world . so we can take it . on our viewport and our
viewport is actually this white thing which year the y 2 square
so if you put is what we can see
and we need to take the bottom right here and translate that into a well
coordinate so we know we don't exceed the living here in India and this is
just the unit's good preference here i'm just going to show you that if we look
at this view for space is normalized like this
the bottom left of the camera is called 0.0 the top right is called 1.1
so if we look at that will see the bottom left is called 0.0
it's down here and just move this camera so right there
and at this one up here is called 1.1 which means that this one down here
should be called 1.0 because one in 2010 and 1.1 and 1.0 over here
so this . 1.0 is what we need to get the actual world a coordinate from and we
need to translate it into a world space coordinate it your back to free and make
sure that that one doesn't exceed the limits here
so with that in place
I hope you understand what we're going to do then we're going to write some
code
so open up your camera movement script and in here we need to create a new
function so make a private void set limits
and I get my keys correctly and I can't let go and it needs to change in
something but we will handle that in a second
first of all we need the world coordinate of the right side of the
camera here so we go
one . not zero . zero then we go one out on the x-axis and we still in surround
the y-axis so it's 1.0 here
so this is the point we need so we can say vector free
it's called p equals camera the main . viewport fort to world . we take our
camera and this actually access is the main camera and we need to take a point
on the viewport and the viewport . we need is a new litter free called in 1.0
to go
so this is the right bottom corner of the screen we translate into a
coordinate here which is saved in
it's got it's just going to be p world .
here we go ok so the next thing we need to do is to get the actual point of the
next I'll or the the amount of what's called in range we can move and to do
that we'll have to access the actual tile down here
we need to get this tile and calculate the distance from here to the camera so
that we know how much we can actually move and the same goal from - from the
top here to the bottom because this little tile down here and here the point
right here is actually our limit right
we need to get that . and make sure that this corner doesn't go over this corner
so
we need a victor free and it's called max tiles this is the position of that
make style
so we need an X limit and why limit
so let's go up here and make a private its limit
it's max it's called that research is going to be a float and then make a
private flowed called why mix so this is going to be a limit for the x value and
this is going to be the limit for the y value
ok now we have some burgers to store this limited next thing we have to do is
to say the xmax people to make style . x minus the world . . x so if we take the
next house position
- the world . position then we have how much we can move right because we have a
tile somewhere say out here take that position - this position then we know
how much we can move and we have to do this implies so why max equal to the
next I'll y equals world . . of why go and let's save this
so now we have the functions were doing this but we need to call the set limits
and set the next I'll so we will do this in a little bit in a smart way later
when we have added a helper class and everything but for now we just going to
use do it the easiest way
it's not the best way to do it and but it's the most ahead and wait for us
right now to do this thing
so if we go to the liver manager and then we have to add something to the
what do you call the crate level function here
let's find it right here and that means simply going to create a vector free
called max time you have to set it equal to break free . 0 if you don't do this
then it's going to complain and tell you that you're trying to use on and sign
variable so we just have to set it equal to something so down here when we place
a tile we actually gets the position down here when we set the transformer
station right here right in the playstyle function so every time we
place a tile we just return that we can return that position and when we're done
we always get the latest latest i'll because we start placing our tiles from
the top down here all waited once like this and the last time child place is
always this one down here so this is not the best way as i told you to do this we
will do it in a better way where we only access the style right now we are going
to set the max time position to equal to the next time we play so every time
replace a tile the next I'll will be equal to a new position and when we're
done it will end up with this is precision
so we can simply just rewrite our next I'll and see terms of its free and then
we simply need to
return new tile that transformed the position
so now it actually returns the position of the towel which is placed
so we can go up here and say next I'll equals this type of place to mix that
will now be equal to the towel we just play so now we will have the position of
the actual child that we are going to and place in the end
now we need to use this map tile next aisle and give this feat this to the set
limits function here as you can see here we need the vector free next time
and so we need to call that and to do so we can actually make a private camera
and movement really wasn't that him a movement there
yeah so we have a camera movement up here and we can simply just socialize it
split it with with this with the childproof caps so we can see the
inspector and then we can go down here after our fall to peer just after it
not inside but after my camera movement that set limits and you can see we can
see set limits here
that's because i made it private i think so go to camera movement and set limits
make it public like so and save and jump back to live in manager and right camera
movement again and set limits and then it needs the position which is max tile
go
so now we are executing the camera movements that limits and with we're
feeding at the next I'll hear them
yeah ok so this is not enough we need to add some functionality to the camera
movement and to make this work
so for example if we save this that right now and a jump to unity and select
our little manager here take the main camera and move the main camera into the
camera movement apart here and we start playing the game
well then we can still move
freely around here up and down and I can move too much to the left here and and
if you see then i'll still be able to move over in the right side here so this
doesn't didn't really change anything
and why is that well we're not using the limits for anything right now
so we have to jump back into the script and go to camera movement and down here
we have to write some coach you limit the movement of the camera so we have to
use a clamp to claim the movement
so we can actually say transform that position equals new Victor free so we
take the position after we have moved the camera up here we take and clamp the
position by saying math if the clamp and clamping is in the way of making sure
that value doesn't exceed it
these are the values we put in here so we can't the position to a new vector
free where we use transform position X and it shouldn't be able to go below
zero and it shouldn't be able to go or x max here and then the Y value should be
mass eff . claimed that a strange form the position that why command 0 , max
cool and actually it shouldn't be wimax because we're going down
so actually we should we should actually rename this one click on it press of two
and ride
why minimum instead of Max and then we should use it as the minimum value here
as you can see what I'm riding here it asks for the minimum value which is why
minimum and 0 because yeah I for that we're going downward so we should switch
it's not my maximum is not the top with the bottom we are looking at button of
tile as you remember
ok so now we have something that sets the limit
so if we save this
and jump back into unity then there's still some problems as you can see now
we can't even see anything here but i am one on there on this front I'll see what
I can't see anything
and the reason of that is because the sea position here of the camera is 0 and
keep setting it to 0 you can even change it to something else
so we need to make sure that our is the position here is a example - 10 so we
give the better for a year after your comment - -
now we set the MC position as - 10 so that we can go here
play the game and now you can see you imagine because the camera is further
away from the task force on top of the tiles and then the tires go through the
camera can't see them so now we just climate in in climbing into this
position here is that but i'm not able to move quickly around as you can see
here
I'm missing one length of the tiles here
I'm not going to the pitch you have to see but i'm going to this edge and I
can't move out but that's fine but i can move to for far down and and I and I'm
fine so over-the-top the left side on the top side is correct but the bottom
and the right side is wrong
so we need to do something here and that's inside our little manager when we
set the limits
we are missing something we need to use the width of the tiles to make sure that
we actually use the correct values so we need to say knew Victor free and we need
to share
next I'll 2x plus tile size ,
next I'll . why - tile size
so these are the values so now we're creating a new vector free as the next
i'll be using the next position posted
Plus tile size so we get that extra tile size out and as you can see we were
going too far down as you can see here we were missing one tile
so we need to
that's how sighs to the limits and as you can see here we are going to far
down so we need to reduce the amount of space we can move down there with the
height of the size of these tiles
so , -
tile size that that - nice to have that why - tile size here so let's try to
save this and jump back into unity and we run the game
so if we run the game now
you could see that the x value here fits perfectly it goes to the edge here and
it can go up but if you go down you're still able to move too far down to need
to figure out why we can exceed the limits in the button and I have an idea
why but let's take a look at it and figure out what's wrong because we're
going way too far down here so let's try to open them
the camera movement script find the arrow and I always see the arrow here in
my set limits function i wrote my style y equals vp that why so it should be
- year repeat that why and its trying to save it again
so now it should actually calculate the minimum value of y better
maybe you already caught this earlier when i was writing this and maybe you're
screaming at just waiting for me to change it but yeah now I tested it now
figure out that this was the problem so jump back into unity run your game right
here and now you shouldn't be able to go to that they're too far here
so as you can see here now the limits I actually correct
you can't go over the right edge you can't go over the bottom image and you
can't go over the top and the and the left side here
so now we have a camera that can pen and round on our level no matter how large
it will get and so that's it for this video in the next video will start
adding some more functionality for and
the actual gameplay i think but let's see what we're going to do and thank you
very much for watching and remember that in scope students is a community found
page and that's why you guys report is very important to me you can support in
different ways you can follow me on social media pages you can subscribe to
this channel and and you can also support me by am getting all my projects
you can do that on the patreon page in the top of the screen right here and if
you support me you'll just get all projects that have ever created for
materials and you will also be able to in it private tutoring is that what you
want to in the bottom you can support me by getting one of my projects as a
standalone product so and thank you very much for watching